Guide to the Rogers Family Collection 1759-1993 MS 029 MS 029 MS 029
Cornwall Historical Society
Rogers Family Collection
1759-1993
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 029
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection consists of documents relating to the Rogers family of Cornwall, principally Edward Rogers (1735-1813) as well as his brother Noah Rogers III (1731-1810) and several of their children and grandchildren.
Provenance
The collection is the product of several separate acquisitions by the Cornwall Historical Society. In the early 1990s, the various donations, purchases, and collected items were combined to form the current collection.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection consists of documents relating to the Rogers family of Cornwall, principally Edward Rogers (1735-1813) as well as his brother Noah Rogers III (1731-1810) and several of their children and grandchildren. The two men were sons of Noah Rogers, Jr. (1688-1760) and originally from Branford, Connecticut. During the French and Indian War, Edward marched through the Cornwall area, and in 1760, he and his brother Noah moved to the community. The two brothers and their descendants were prominent farmers and businessmen in the community and were especially active in local military matters and religious life.
Scope and Content Note
The items relating to Edward Rogers provide unique information on farming in Cornwall, and due to his prominent status in community affairs, also shed light on Revolutionary War-era tax information and on local judicial proceedings. His livestock receipts involve business dealings with community members such as Jonathan Crocker, Samuel Butler Jr., Samuel Marble, and Jacob Cumming. The collection contains information on two of Edward’s sons, Anson and Edward, Jr., and on several generations of Noah’s descendants, namely: his son Noah IV; grandchildren Ambrose, Daniel L., and Noah V, and great-grandchildren, Henry L., Miner, Egbert, Dwight, and Mary E. Several individuals with unknown direct connections to the family are also included in the collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by person/group then chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Noah Rogers, Jr.
Edward Rogers
Noah Rogers III
Descendents
Miscellaneous
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Receipts (financial records); Correspondence; military records; Cornwall Historical Society; Rogers, Edward (1735-1813); Rogers III, Noah (1731-1810); Rogers Jr., Noah (1688-1760)
- Noah Rogers, Jr.
  - Itemized list of moveable estate, 1756 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Edward Rogers
  - Inventory of Edward Rogers Papers, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Militia appointment, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Receipts for purchased livestock, 1766-1786 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
  - Receipts for Cornwall taxes paid to colony/state government, 1772-1780 (Box 1, Folder 10-21)
  - Receipt for horse and riding equipment, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Receipt for side saddle, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Receipt with Daniel Furran, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Receipt with William Light, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Heirs receipt with Alex Lamb, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Note from Thomas Dickinson, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter from Charles Caldwell, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with Bartholomew Heath, 1792-1793 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
  - Obligation of H. and S. Stuard to pay Rogers constable fees, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Binding agreement with Oliver Wolcott, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letter sent from Oliver Wolcott to Rogers, John Sedgwick, and Benjamin Gold, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Invitation to judicial meeting, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Accounts exhibited against estate of Elias White, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letter from L. Whitney, regarding prisoner, John Pangborn, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Complaint against James Wilcox for Sabbath-breaking, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Order for Ebenezer Jackson to pay John Jones, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Obligation of A. and D. Young to pay Rogers constable fees, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Property rates and abatements, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - List of people with accounts in “old books", 1783 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Account book page, 1783-1784 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Note with Mr. Hart, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Account book page, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Note with John Hundy, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Note with R. Mildon, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Noah Rogers III
  - Deed with Joshua Lathrop, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Deed with Gilbert Harris, et al., 1795 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Ambrose Rogers
    - Letter to Leete Rogers, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Genealogical remarks, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Anson Rogers
    - Bill from T. G. H. Baldwin, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Bill from W. Hills, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Militia appointments, 1815-1829 (Box 1, Folder 55-60)
    - Letter from Edward Rogers, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Correspondence with F. W. Miner, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 62-63)
    - Account with Landon Hehunt, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Receipts for local taxes paid, 1815-1817 (Box 1, Folder 65-66)
    - Receipt for cloth, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Receipt from Nicholas Thorne, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Receipt for calico, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - State tax orders, 1825-1830 (Box 1, Folder 70-72)
    - Receipts for state taxes, 1824-1825 (Box 1, Folder 73-74)
    - Postmaster appointment, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Letters from O. Seymour and B. Skinner, about postal appointments, 1853-1861 (Box 1, Folder 76-77)
  - Daniel L. Rogers
    - Deeds, 1817-1867 (Box 1, Folder 78-104)
    - Militia appointment, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Letter from J. C. Rogers, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Correspondence with Elisa Norton, 1849; , undated (Box 1, Folder 107-108)
    - Correspondence with O. R. Burnham, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 109-112)
    - Letter from Mary M. Rogers, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Letter from E. M. Pratt, undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Surveys and plats of farm, 1847-1854 (Box 1, Folder 115-116)
    - Account with M. Beers Sons, 1863-1869 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - Probate information, 1869-1870 (Box 1, Folder 118)
- Descendants
  - David Leete Rogers
    - Letter to Edward Strong, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter from J. C. Rogers, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letter from A. R. Pratt, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letter from A. T. Norton, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letter from T. D. Rogers, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letter from “Abbie", 1866 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dwight Rogers
    - Deeds, 1864-1889 (Box 2, Folder 7-17)
    - Correspondence with family in Cornwall from New York City Hospital, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Letter from W. C. and M. E. Rogers, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter and bill from Rogers Farm Dairy, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letter from R. R. Pratt, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Diary, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Abstract of land, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Edward Rogers, Jr.
    - Indenture with John Ward, 1814 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Egbert M. Rogers
    - Deeds, 1857-1876 (Box 2, Folder 26-36)
    - Letter from O. R. Burnham, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Description of land, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Henry L. Rogers
    - Deeds, 1847-1870 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - J. A. R. Rogers
    - Letter to “uncle and aunt", 1867 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - J. C. Rogers
    - Letter sent to “Brother", 1854 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Letter sent to Leete Rogers, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Leete Rogers
    - Deed from Noah Rogers, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Militia appointment, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lucy Leete Rogers Papers
    - Religious devotional by Lucy Leete, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Covenant," and "Creed," tracts by Lucy Leete, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "Notes of Sermons," by Lucy Leete, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Letter regarding church membership of Lucy Leete Rogers, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Letter from E. L. Leete to "wife", 1866 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Mary E. Rogers
    - Account book, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Miner P. Rogers
    - Letter from William H. Porter, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Letter from Daniel Rogers, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Letter sent to "sister", 1863 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Deeds, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 55-56)
  - Noah Rogers IV
    - Deeds, 1787-1830 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence with Stephen Eno, 1788-1790 (Box 2, Folder 58-61)
    - State order for tax collection, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Bond with Daniel Brown, 1806-1815 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Copy of petition to county sheriff, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Marriage agreement with Abigail Humphrey, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - List of quitclaimed property, 1866-1870 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Description of Ward Lot, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - List of land purchases, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Distribution of estate, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Noah Rogers V
    - Letter sent to E. C. Starr, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Newspaper article, "Farm Lessons for Connecticut," by Noah Rogers, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - William H. Rogers
    - Deed with William H. Scoville, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Miscellaneous
  - Almanacs, 1850-1858 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Receipt of B. Barstal from Peris Bonney, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cornwall tax lists, 1777-1779 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Guilty verdict against Ebenezer Dickinson for fathering Mary Clother’s illegitimate child, 1781 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Complaint against Levi Pierce, for assault, 1789 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letter to John Jeffers from Robert McClure, 1797 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Receipt of John Reed from Elias Jackson, 1797 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Note to John C. Smith from Nathaniel Holly, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Note to "Mr. Rogers" from J. H. North, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Deed from S. H. Milton to Harvey Baldwin, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - N. Scoville appointment as postmaster, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Deed from James Blake to Seelye Hart, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Warning out notice to Silas Ackly, and co., undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Plat of Rogers land in the Hollow, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Property list from unspecified Rogers farm, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Survey of unspecified Rogers property, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Order to Ebenezer Cotter to organize military parade, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - E.C. Starr’s Rogers Family Documents
    - Order to Edward Rogers regarding J. Keith v. S. Butler, 1769 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Postmaster appointment of Anson Rogers, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - D. Rogers’ grocery bill, 1878-1879 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - J. A. R. Rogers correspondence with E. C. Starr, 1895-1908 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
    - Editorials by J. A. R. Rogers, undated (Box 3, Folder 27-31)
    - Items relating to J. A. R. Rogers’ founding of Berea College, undated (Box 3, Folder 32-35)
    - Sermons by J. A. R. Rogers, undated (Box 3, Folder 36-38)
    - Photograph of J. A. R. Rogers and Elizabeth Rogers, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Obituaries of J. A. R. Rogers, undated (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
    - Newspaper image of Rev. Daniel M. Rogers, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Letter from M.H. Rogers to E.C. Starr, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Newspaper clipping about M. H. Rogers, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Newspaper image of M.H. Rogers, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Rogers family vital records, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Provenance
    - Letter sent to J. N. Norwood from V. A. Phillips, about Rogers family bible, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Letter sent to Cornwall Historical Society from C. A. Rogers, Jr., regarding family information, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence of Paula Holmes, regarding acquisition of Rogers documents, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 49-53)
    - List of items auctioned off from Gunnar Rogers items, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence between Cornwall Historical Society and Nancy Beveridge, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 55)